Standard, William Papers 5258
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Standard Papers
1934-1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Standard, William
5258
9.33 cubic feet
9.3 linear ft.
Records (documents), broadsides (notices), case files, newspaper clippings, decisions, photographs.
This collection consists of William L. Standard's files as General Counsel for the National Maritime Union [NMU]. It documents public policy toward the NMU during World War II; the status of the Merchant Marine under the U.S. War Shipping Administration; the politics of Joseph E. Curran (president, NMU); collective negotiations between the NMU and various railroads and shipping companies; and work stoppages conducted by the NMU. This collection also documents Standard's duties as the union's representative in lobbying for legislation and in litigation before the National Labor Relations Board, federal and state civil courts, the War Shipping Administration and the Bureau of Marine Inspection and Navigation.
3833892
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 29, 1999
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, March 08, 2019
Biographical / Historical
William L. Standard was a lawyer who specialized in admiralty law, specifically in the welfare of merchant seamen. He served as the General Counsel for the National Maritime Union [NMU] from 1937 to 1948. Prior to the founding of the NMU in 1937, he was legal counsel to the Marine Workers Industrial Union and the International Seaman's Union, AFL. In 1948, Standard's contract was terminated as part of a broader movement in the NMU to rid itself of Communists and perceived far-left members. Mr. Standard went on to be a senior partner at the firm of Standard, Wiesberg, Heckerling and Rossow. He also published books opposing America's involvement in the Vietnam War and on the history of merchant seamen. He passed away in 1978.
Biographical / Historical
The National Maritime Union [NMU] was an American labor union representing merchant seamen. It was founded in May 1937 by Joseph Curran, Ferdinand Smith, and M. Hedley Stone after a split from the International Seafarer's Union, AFL. It affiliated with the Congress of Industrial Organizations [CIO] at its first convention in July 1937. It was at this same convention that approximately 30,000 seamen left the ISU to join the NMU. By the end of the year, the NMU had over 50,000 members and contracts with most American shipping concerns.
Joseph Curran was elected president of the NMU and served as such until 1981. Ferdinand Smith, a Jamaican-born man of Afro-Caribbean descent, was its first vice-president; M. Hedley Stone was its first secretary-treasurer. The leadership of the NMU had strong Communist ties. Among the notable reforms achieved by the union's Communist-dominated leadership was "checkerboarding," the side-by-side racial integration of sailors' sleeping quarters. Another innovation of the new union was the formation of hiring halls in each port. The hiring halls ensured a steady supply of experienced seamen for passenger and cargo ships, and reduced the corruption which plagued the hiring of able seamen. The hiring halls also worked to combat racial discrimination and promote racial harmony among maritime workers. By the end of World War II, the NMU had nearly 100,000 members.
During World War II, the alliance of Communists and non-Communists in the union was weakened. The Cold War exacerbated the ideological divide, and in 1948, the NMU's Communist leadership and its allies were defeated in union elections and expelled. Joseph Curran had distanced himself from the communist elements and in fact helped purge the NMU of any Communist-affiliated members.
The NMU merged with the Seafarers International Union of North America in 2001.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1934-1950
Bulk dates: 1939- 1948
This collection consists of the files of NMU's General Counsel William Standard. The records in this collection document the activities of the NMU in its early years. This includes records on legislation affecting the NMU and its members; hearings in front of the National War Labor Board, the National Labor Relations Board, and the War Shipping Administration; negotiations and arbitrations conducted by the NMU on behalf of its members with various corporations and in front of a Presidential Emergency Board; legal files including case notes, filings, and briefs filed in U.S. District and Supreme Courts on a variety of issues including defending NMU members from accusations of seditious activities and in court-martial proceedings, as well as defending the NMU from libelous news stories printed by newspapers owned by the Hearst publishing empire; files on strikes, including the National Maritime Strike of 1946; and general files on the NMU itself and its organizational structure.
Legislative files include drafts of bills, memoranda, letters and reports regarding the National Maritime Union's lobbying activities and its position on federal legislation of interest to its members. The bulk of these records concerns maritime legislation enacted during or immediately after World War II and includes documentation on proposed amendments to War Shipping Administration regulations; on the Merchant Seamen's War Service Act; on suspension of provisions of the Public Vessels Act of 1925; on seamen's rehabilitation legislation; on proposed amendments to the Merchant Marine Act; on amendments to the National Service Life Insurance Act; and on amendments to the Railway Labor Act. This legislation and other bills documented in these files sought to expedite the activities of merchant seamen during the war, to minimize work stoppages, to compensate families of deceased seamen, to provide vocational rehabilitation for those disabled as a result of war-related injuries, to provide for the naturalization of foreign seamen who served on American owned vessels, and to protect the merchant marine from wartime sabotage. The union was also interested in such legislation as the Taft-Hartley amendments to the National Labor Relations Act and anti-organized labor legislation that began appearing in some states after the war.
National War Labor Board case files include statements, letters, decisions, and proposals for cases brought before the Board. The issues brought before the Board include working conditions, wages, hours of work, dispute settlement, jurisdiction, union security, union activity, and collective negotiations.
The National Labor Relations Board case files on NMU representation elections include correspondence, petitions for certification, authorization cards and supporting documentation on certification elections brought before the Board.
The War Shipping Administration case files consist of agreements, letters and petitions regarding cases of the NMU before the War Shipping Administration on the issues of wages and the allocation of personnel on the steamships Copley and Wheeler.
Arbitration case files include awards, decisions, memoranda, and statements pertaining to cases involving various arbitrators. The issues include overtime pay, impasses in collective negotiations, hiring, seniority, discrimination, grievance procedure, and holidays.
Files on collective negotiations include materials pertaining to bargaining conducted between the NMU and various railroads and shipping companies. The documents consist of copies of collective agreements, letters, and statements of proposals of the parties. These files also include materials pertaining to the mediation proceedings held by the National Mediation Board to resolve an impasse in collective negotiations between the NMU and the Reading Railroad tugboat operators.
Files on legal cases argued on behalf of the NMU before the U.S. District and Supreme Courts and various military courts include correspondence, notes and various legal documents. These files include a libel case between the NMU and various newspapers because of a published report alleging NMU members refused to unload military supplies on Guadalcanal Island. Also found is the case file regarding the court martial of an NMU member, in which Standard seeks to determine what level of jurisdiction the Articles of War have over merchant seamen on non-military vessels. Finally, there is documentation of the settlement of strikes against various Great Lakes transportation companies by the NMU.
Standard maintained general files on NMU activities and issues, largely during the war years. These include data on the national reorganization of the union in 1939; on pension and benefit claims and regulations; on the relationship of the NMU to the Women's Auxiliary of the American Merchant Marine Institute, Inc.; and on sedition trials of NMU members. Of particular interest in these files are documents relating to alleged racial discrimination in employment on the Atlantic Coast Line Company; the position of Joseph E. Curran (president, NMU) regarding a Supreme Court case concerning Communist affidavits in 1948; and documents relating to FBI investigations of the NMU and the CIO.
Also in the collection are two scrapbooks of news clippings and articles regarding various strikes and elections, non-union workers, salaries, collective agreements, court decisions, safety, hazards, accidents, disasters, factional disputes in maritime unions, communism in unions, and copies of NMU news bulletins dating from 1943 to 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5118: New York City Board of Transportation and the Transport Workers Union Records 5251: New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Hearing Transcripts and Records
Arbitration, Industrial -- Merchant marine -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Merchant marine -- United States; Communism -- United States; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry -- United States; Disability insurance -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Emigration and immigration law--United States.; Employee fringe benefits -- Merchant marine -- United States; Foreign workers -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Labor rest homes -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Lobbyists; Merchant marine -- United States -- Manning of vessels; Merchant mariners; Merchant mariners -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Naturalization--United States.; Political crimes and offenses -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Social security -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Merchant marine -- United States; Subversive activities -- United States; Merchant mariners -- Labor unions -- United States; Government vessels -- United States; Wages -- Merchant marine -- United States; War and emergency powers -- United States; War risk insurance -- United States; Workers' compensation -- Merchant marine -- United States; Working conditions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Bridges, Harry, 1901-1990; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Smith, Ferdinand C.; Standard, William L.; Stone, M. Hedley (Murray Hedley).; American Merchant Marine Institute; American Merchant Marine Institute. Women's Auxiliary; Ann Arbor Railroad Company; Associated Press; Atlantic Coast Line Company; Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Co.; Atlantic Steamship Company; Automotive Steamship Lines; Bethlehem Transportation Company; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Ford Motor Company; Grand Trunk Western Railroad Company; Great Lakes Shipping Company; Gulf Steamship Company; Hearst Consolidated Publications; Isthmian Steamship Company; National Maritime Union of America; New York Joint Maritime Strike Committee; Nicholson Transit Company; Pan American Refining Corporation; Panama Railroad Company; Pere Marquette Railway; Pittsburgh Supply Company; Polarus Steamship Company; Reading Company; Richfield Oil Corporation; Standard Fruit and Steamship Company; Standard Oil Company; United States. Labor Management Relations Act, 1947; United States. Public Vessels Act (Liability); United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; United States. National Labor Relations Board; United States. National Mediation Board; United States. National Service Life Insurance Act of 1940; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. Railway Labor Act; United States. War Shipping Administration; Wabash Railroad
3833892
- American Merchant Marine Institute Negotiations, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Car Ferries. Ann Arbor Railroad Co., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  In re representation for Car Ferry workers by NMU; case before the National Mediation Board, case A-2420. Also negotiations for 40-Hour Work Week.
- Car Ferries. Pere Marquette Co., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Agreement
- Car Ferries. Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains specific files regarding Ann Arbor Railroad Company, Detroit River and Lake Michigan, general mediation notes, Grand Trunk and Western Railroad Company, Great Lakes Car Ferry, Pere Marquette Railroad Company, Reading Railroad Car Ferry and Wabash
- Car Ferries. National Mediation Board. Correspondence and notes., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Car Ferries. Grand Trunk and Western Railroad Co., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Car Ferries. Wabash Railroad, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Car Ferries. Pere Marquette Railroad, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Car Ferries. Reading Railroad, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Contains annotated copy of 1936 Washington Jobs Agreement and receipt for a petty cash withdrawal.
- Great Lakes. General, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Organizing
- Great Lakes. Bulk freighter and tanker companies., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes correspondence between the NMU and Ford Motor Company, Inland Steel and International Harvester regarding the opening of contract negotiations; Great Lakes Bulk Freight Agreement negotiations with Bethlehem Transportation Corporation, Brown and C
- Great Lakes. Tanker Agreement, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes newspaper clipping from The NMU Pilot
- Great Lakes. Inland Waterways Corporation (owned by the U.S. Government), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes correspondence regarding challenging the right to apply Civil Service laws to Federal Barge Line employees; Government Corporation Control Act; Federal Employee Pay Act; general correspondence from the committee for Rivers Unity regarding a strik
- Municipal and Government Employees. Collective Bargaining., 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  With regard to the New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee hearings.
- Panama Railroad Company, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes correspondence regarding employee coverage under the Unemployment Insurance Law.
- Pan American Refining Corporation, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  In re tugs and barges.
- Car Ferries. Emergency Board No. 63. Transcript. [folder 1 of 2], 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17a)
  In re Pere Marquette (C&O subsidiary railroad), Ann Arbor Railroad Co., Wabash Railroad, and Grand Trunk Western Railroad Arbitration with NMU.
- Emergency Board No. 63. Exhibits. [folder 2 of 2], 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17b)
- Great Lakes. Polaris Steamship Company, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Car Ferries. Reading Railroad Tugboats, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Texas Company, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Contains agreements on behalf of the personnel of the SS Maine and SS Michigan and an agreement with Standard Oil.
- Union Exhibits in Arbitration, Wage Review Under Standard Passenger - Freighter Contract, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Car Ferries. Wabash Railroad Company, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Wabash Railroad Company, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Herman Rosenfeld's file
- Austin, Kenneth, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Includes correspondence regarding alleged subversive activities by Mr. Austin.
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 1 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Initial conflict between Seaman Berue and his Captain was a result of the captain's anti-Semitic abuse of Seaman Berue. Correspondence from the accused, his wife, U.S. State Department officials, U.S. Navy leadership, and Mr. Standard.
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 2 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Found in this folder is the Writ of Habeas Corpus filed by Mr. Standard. Also contains case note in re whether a merchant seaman may be subject to the Articles of War and as such may be court-martialed under them.
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 3 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Includes copy of court martial transcript and correspondence with several government agencies.
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 4 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 5 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 6 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 7 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 8 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Berue, Jacob M., Court Martial [Folder 9 of 9], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Callwood, Leopold v. Curran, Joseph (president, NMU), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Janitor in NMU's Manhattan headquarters, claim for wages.
- De Zon vs. American President Lines, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Liability under the Jones Act. Correspondence and filing before the Supreme Court (not W. Standard's case).
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 1 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Includes copy of Coast Guard investigation into the accidental death of Joseph Donnellan Jr., coroner's report and numerous photo's of accident site.
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 2 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 3 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 4 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 5 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 6 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Donnellan, Joseph vs. Atlantic Gulf and Pacific Company [Folder 7 of 7], 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Empire Personal Loan vs. Louis Orfe, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Free Trade Enterprises Inc., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes handwritten notes, copies of documents filed in Circuit, Appellate and Supreme Courts.
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Great Lakes Wage and Overtime Dispute, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Libel Cases. NMU v. Akron Beacon Journal, Associated Press (re Guadalcanal story), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Also NMU adv. Hearst Consolidated Publications, Inc.
- Libel Cases. NMU v. Akron Beacon Journal, Associated Press (re Guadalcanal story), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Libel Cases. NMU v. Akron Beacon Journal, Associated Press (re Guadalcanal story), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Los Angeles newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Philadelphia newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Correspondence from union members looking for clippings in local papers drawing from the allegedly libelous wire story.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press, Hearst Consolidated Publications, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  In re the Guadalcanal story.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press, Hearst Consolidated Publications, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  In re Guadalcanal story. Newspaper clippings of printed retractions.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press, Hearst Consolidated Publications, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Correspondence in re Guadalcanal story, letters of support for NMU.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Baltimore newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  In re Guadalcanal story.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Chicago newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  In re Guadalcanal story. Contain filing against The Chicago Tribune.
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Milwaukee newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. The Associated Press (New Orleans newspapers), 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Libel Cases. Finnish newspaper, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Libel Cases. NMU adv. Philadelphia Daily News, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Libel Cases. Libelous West Coast Attack., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- McCune. Court Martial. Newport News, VA, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Great Lakes. Nicholson Transit Company, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- NMU v. Westbrook Pegler (Collier's Weekly columnist), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Includes several broadsides denouncing slander of the National Maritime Union (NMU). Not a libel case, but response of union to attack columns in weekly magazine.
- NMU v. Edward Rickenbacker (Life magazine columnist), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Contains Life magazine article slandering the NMU.
- Rusin's Case. Warner Co. v. Augustus Norton, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  William Standard filed Amicus brief with the Supreme Court to argue for the protection of bargemen working alongside longshoremen.
- Shipmen's dismissal for alleged Subversive Activities, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Strikes. Arrest of NMU Members for Posting Stickers in NYC Subway, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Stickers in support of Nationwide Maritime Strike.
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. Car Ferries., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. General., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. General., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. Great Lakes., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. Great Lakes., 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. General., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Strikes. Nationwide Maritime Strike. Legal Committee., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Strikes. National Maritime Strike. Pere Marquette Railroad Company, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Strikes. Standard Oil., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Contains daily reports of progress being made in the strike against Standard Oil.
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Includes newspaper clippings regarding their negotiations.
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- NWLB. NMU adv. American Merchant Marine Institute, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- NWLB. NMU adv. Army Transport Service, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)